<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Liu's ePortfolio</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://liu2z2.github.io/</id><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Modular Garden Monitoring System (Senior Design Project)</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20210501-modular-garden-monitoring-system-senior-design-project" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2021-05-01:/articles/20210501-modular-garden-monitoring-system-senior-design-project</id><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe id="lbry-iframe" width="560" height="315" src="https://odysee.com/$/embed/mgms/3dc55404ac7641b69029c516e8d3dc4355a71381?r=CSvAscaSzRs3YGifseotXHHmkb7njV6C" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>Gate-Level Control Unit Design</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20210426-gate-level-control-unit-design" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2021-04-26:/articles/20210426-gate-level-control-unit-design</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This article talks about the technical aspects and takeaway from two inter-connecting projects from Intro to Computer Architecture and Organization Class.
The detail about the class is explained in my &lt;a href="../Discussion/spring-2021.md"&gt;Spring 2021 Remark&lt;/a&gt;.
More info about the projects is available at my &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/class-files/tree/main/spring2021-comp-org"&gt;class-files repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="non-pipelined-control-unit"&gt;Non-Pipelined Control Unit&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#non-pipelined-control-unit" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single-bus processing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This article talks about the technical aspects and takeaway from two inter-connecting projects from Intro to Computer Architecture and Organization Class.
The detail about the class is explained in my &lt;a href="../Discussion/spring-2021.md"&gt;Spring 2021 Remark&lt;/a&gt;.
More info about the projects is available at my &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/class-files/tree/main/spring2021-comp-org"&gt;class-files repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="non-pipelined-control-unit"&gt;Non-Pipelined Control Unit&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#non-pipelined-control-unit" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single-bus processing unit was designed capable of executing a set of instructions specified as in Fig. 1.
The design was implemented at the gate level. Some restrictions of the assignment include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design should be restricted to single-bus paradigm. No point-to-point connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read-only memory (ROM) may be used to contain up to 8 constants. Its design can be specified descriptively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main memory (MM) design can be specified descriptively and performs asynchronously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gate level design must only use MUX, DEMUX, encoder, decoder, flip-flop and gates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detailed count-down timer design can be specified descriptively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/instr-table.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 1: Instruction set &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="solution-brief"&gt;Solution Brief&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#solution-brief" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We presented our design in a modular structure, which of which is used extensively by the CPU to meet the design requirements and achieve optimization.
An abstract overview of the CPU is shown in Fig. 2.
Data used in the instructions is pushed to a 16-bit bus as the only conveyance before being delivered to the intended locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/data-path.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 2: Abstract view of the data path &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the Control Unit design by firstly defining the control signals needed in each instructions, during which we also discussed necessary changes and possible optimizations in the data path.
The common fetch-decode-execute sequence was adopted as a general guideline.
Afterwards, the control signals are collapsed into groups such that states can be determined, as well as the state transition.
With the aforementioned state information narrowed down, the gate-level circuit was implemented as a Moore machine whose input is Opcode and various control flags from other components on the data bus, and whose output is to enable tri-state buffers on data paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/state-trans.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 3: State transition diagram &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/control-unit.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 4: Control unit block component view &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detail on other components is explained in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/class-files/tree/main/fall2021-comp-org/project-3-report.pdf"&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;. Related optimizations include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We use Y and Z as pre- and post- buffer for the ALU operations, respectively, by statically writing in common register values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insead of sending six different control signals to dictate ALU functions for Opcode 0-5, whose operands are in similar format, the control unit commences a master signal which lets the ALU requests the Opcode directly to decide on the specific logical/arithmetic operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ALU utilizes a carry lookahead adder-subtractor circuit in order to add or subtract two 16-bit values and output a single 16-bit value.
  The carry lookahead generator, while it utilizes more gates than the
  ripple-carry adder design, results in a significant decrease in propagation delay and performance time through the operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/data-path-block.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig 5: Data path block diagram &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="takeaway"&gt;Takeaway&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#takeaway" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we went through the design and part of the implementation phase of a digital/register level project.
We broke down the specification, explored possible solution, discussed possible optimization and eventually documented our solution within the time constraints.
As a class assignment, we have scored the highest grade with a few points taken off due to formatting inconsistency.
The project also gave us a chance to reflect on our understanding of the material, and luckily we were given enough time to clarify some questions over the discussion of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pipelined-control-unit"&gt;Pipelined Control Unit&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#pipelined-control-unit" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we were assigned to design a CPU with almost the same functionality, except the operation can be pipelined, and that the gate-level implementation is not required.
Other limitations include I/O constraints, register space capacity, etc, are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No hard restriction on data path, but all paths should be used reasonably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main memory (MM) has separate instruction and data ports that can be used simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register file (GPR) has 3 read ports and 2 write ports and all can be accessed simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pipeline should include at least three stages, corresponding to the fetch/decode/execute cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read-only memory (ROM) may be used to contain up to 8 constants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="solution-brief_1"&gt;Solution Brief&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#solution-brief_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the functionality of this machine has many parts that overlap with the previous project, the detailed design and implementation were only briefly covered, whereas the pipeline is mainly discussed in the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our pipeline design consists of four unique stages: F1, F2, D1 and E1, matching the fetch/decode/execute cycle instruction cycle (Figure 6).
Although some states share hardware resources, each has its own portion of the data path and dedicated portion of the control unit.
By this design, each state only uses 1 clock cycle to finish, resulting in an ideal instruction completion time of 4 clock cycles - with a possible 4 instructions in the pipeline.
Though it was hard to implement such system, this was a firm decision we made at the very beginning and we were determined to resolve the hazards from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/pipeline-timing.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 6: Four stage pipeline &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we decipher the hazards individually, we designed a hardware queue system that dispatches instruction register (IR) and PC data to each stages, ensuring the correct flow of the pipeline.
The implementation of the queuing on IR and PC is 16 stacks of 4-bit and 3-bit shift registers, respectively, shown in Fig. 7.
The memory organization of them can be seen in Fig. 8, where each row is a shift register that can be controlled to shift, keep, or clear on each element, whereas a column represents a full IR/PC data.
Additionally, by having a digitally controlled buffer from the clock to the RESET of the flip-flops, the register can also be cleared synchronously with the rest of the machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/q-mem-org.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 7: Memory organization of the queues &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/shift-reg.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 8: Partial demonstration of shift register control &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, to reflect this queue transition, the control unit commences command for various event during runtime.
The control unit on the top level is demonstrated in Fig. 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/pipeline-control-unit.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 9: Control unit top level design &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stage Controller enables and disables the stages of the pipeline. The Queue Controller keeps the queue in synchronization with the stage behavior by moving forward the shift registers.
At this level, the machine can be seen repeating on a normal state so long as there are no hazards or exceptions.
In the event when they appear, the control unit enters states where it resolves the issue, then go back to looping state.
These states are listed in Fig. 10, along with the GO state when the machine operates normally.
The table also specifies whether to enable specific stages and the control over the queue, which will be justified in sections on hazards and exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/pipeline-states.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 10: States &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural hazards, data hazards and control hazards are addressed separately.
The main idea in our solution is stalling, or descriptively, prioritize execution (E1), and keep other stages from moving, until the hazard is unflagged.
The analysis of each can be found in the project report.
A summary is we exhaust all possible hazards, determined the true conditions, such that the implementation could be as simple as combinatorial gates.
As for control hazards, we were well aware that a dynamic branch predictor is more popular and normally more efficient.
However, since the data path design is determined before considering the control hazards, a limitation is placed to only update PC at execution (E1), making it ineffective even if the predictor predicts “taken”.
Thus, it was decided to use a branch predictor that statically predicts “not taken”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-control-unit/hazard-timing.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Fig. 11: Hazard delay example &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="takeaway_1"&gt;Takeaway&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#takeaway_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the previous assignment, though not requiring a gate-level implementation, this project was more analytically challenging for us as it requires deeper and applicable understanding of pipeline design.
Plus, we also decided on a even more ambitious goal of only allows one step in each stage.
Luckily, with the collective effort of trials and errors, we were able to make sense of everything and deliver the project in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing the project, though not required as an assignment, we hope with capable hardware such as FPGA, we could actually implement both machines to reality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="project"></category><category term="hardware"></category><category term="class"></category></entry><entry><title>Art/Neuroscience Combined Honors Seminar Reflection</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20200617-artneuroscience-combined-honors-seminar-reflection" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2020-06-17:/articles/20200617-artneuroscience-combined-honors-seminar-reflection</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h3 id="class-description"&gt;Class Description&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#class-description" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARTE3041/NS3041: From Neurons to Picasso: How and Why the Brain Makes Art
Offered in Spring Semester 2020
Instructed by Dr. Kris Holland and Dr. Ilya Vilinsky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="reflection-on-class"&gt;Reflection on Class&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#reflection-on-class" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineering student whose research project is related to Brain Computer Interface (BCI), I initially took this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h3 id="class-description"&gt;Class Description&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#class-description" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARTE3041/NS3041: From Neurons to Picasso: How and Why the Brain Makes Art
Offered in Spring Semester 2020
Instructed by Dr. Kris Holland and Dr. Ilya Vilinsky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="reflection-on-class"&gt;Reflection on Class&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#reflection-on-class" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineering student whose research project is related to Brain Computer Interface (BCI), I initially took this seminar to learn the insights about the brain in other disciples. Dr. Holland and Dr. Vilinsky instructed the course well by giving us their expertise, motivating us to think and being welcome to discussion without any judgement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class was conducted by alternate lecture and discussion sessions with a few lab sessions that enhanced the learning experience. Different topics were covered under the discipline of art and neuroscience, including sight mechanism, neuroplasticity, evolution of art, memory, etc. We read class materials that were posted online, then reflect on them in the form of weekly writing assignments (WWA). Since the class partially falls under the study of art, we were also encouraged to take class notes on sketch books rather than ruled notebooks, and embody as much as drawing as possible to illustrate our thoughts. I especially appreciate the fact that other professors were invited in class to participate in discussion on their special research areas. They provided us even more perspectives on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, at the second half of the semester, the class schedule was disoriented by the pandemic. Class material was still posted on weekly basis, but the majority of the time I spent on the class at home was about the final project. The requirement of the final project was broad, so long as it is related to art and (or) neuroscience. At that time, I was learning machine learning (ML) and taking a class on digital image processing, so I decided to work on a project that imitates art styles and interprets them from a programming standpoint. Though the implementation was hard as I was new to ML, I finished it by the deadline with good results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the class itself, it was a meaningful and enjoyable experience, and I believe that it could have been even better if the second half of the semester went as planned. I definitely recommend this course to other students under any major, and I wish this class could continue for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="final-project-showcase"&gt;Final Project Showcase&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#final-project-showcase" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" height="600" src="/ViewerJS/#../docs/HS_final_project.pdf" style="width:100%;" webkitallowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>Developing a Gas Price Tracking and Prediction Application</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20200429-developing-a-gas-price-tracking-and-prediction-application" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2020-04-29:/articles/20200429-developing-a-gas-price-tracking-and-prediction-application</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h3 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is about developing a web application based on data that is related to automobile gas prices. The desired feature of the application is that it collects gas prices at different places every day (specific to stations), recommends the user the cheapest station in the area, reminds the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h3 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#introduction" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is about developing a web application based on data that is related to automobile gas prices. The desired feature of the application is that it collects gas prices at different places every day (specific to stations), recommends the user the cheapest station in the area, reminds the user of an increasing/decreasing trend of the price, and generates a report of gas prices that is helpful to economic analysis. It falls under creativity competency because by the time the project was proposed, there has not been similar tools for this specific application, so it could be hard to decide on how to implement this idea. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience will let me know the process of developing an application skill-wise, during which I would utilize my programming, math and engineering skills to achieve the end goal of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the app will help people save money on their commuting travel. On the other hand, the data I collected would be a useful resource to understand oil-related economy, realize potential problems and possibly propose a solution applicable to the original idea of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="procedure"&gt;Procedure&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#procedure" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I divided the project into a few phases. 1) Setting up the environment and base code; 2) building the database by updating on daily basis; 3) developing a method for data statistics; and 4) developing the application. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first phase took longer than expected because I needed to pick up SQL database, which I did not have too much experience working with before. In addition, I also had to make sure everything is set up well so that the data collected later is comprehensive but easy to manage. Afterwards, at the end of October 2019, the code was put in a computer programmed to run once per day (phase two).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the data collecting process, several issues occurred due to hardware and software, making it inconsistent at a few time stamps, but luckily, they got fixed quickly so the overall data trend was not interrupted. After a few months, the database was found large enough for statistical analysis, so the third phase started after 2019’s Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of this part was also time consuming, as I was trying different statistical tools while also learning database merging methods in order for the source files to look professionally organized. Unfortunately, right after I finished my research and decided a way to implement (at the end of February 2020), COVID-19 hit the country hard. During the time I struggled to adapt to working-from-home environment, I decided to close the project as it is considering two reasons. Firstly, I wanted to prioritize finishing my classes and research until the end of the semester; and secondly, the gas market may have been affected by the pandemic, which is an significantly influential variable that may complicate the case study. Therefore, at the end of the Spring semester 2020, I briefly implemented data visualization by plotting the data per city, and concluded the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical aspect of the project will be explained in the &lt;a href="https://liu2z2.github.io/tags#project-ref"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; category while this reflection mainly focused on the overall execution and the learning experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="results"&gt;Results&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#results" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of the visualized data as of the closing phase of the project are shown in Figures 1, 2 and 3. Plotted in different colors, the mean prices of three gas grades are connected together with respect to time, where there are vertical grey bars whose upper and lower bounds illustrate the max and min price number. Then the three curves are put together in the same plot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/discuss-gastrack/Lexington.webp" width="30%"/&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/discuss-gastrack/Cincinnati.webp" width="30%"/&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/discuss-gastrack/Columbus.webp" width="30%"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing and contrasting the plots result in a few interesting findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fluctuations of the prices in three gas grades share similar patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prices in neighbored areas may increase/decrease at similar time, but the amount may vary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regarding a specific gas grade in one area, lowest price point changes in a similar manner as the mean price, but the max price point is quite stationary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#conclusion" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the end goal of the project was not achieved before closing, the method of web crawling and data mining was proven viable for the intended application, and I believe it can lead to a promising direction if more effort and time are given. Better project management could have been used to improve the productivity, but there are still proud parts in the execution, such as breaking the process down into several phases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, if the project is ever to be continued, there are a few recommendations for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few interruptions in the data collecting phase for various reasons. For example, the program crashed because of unexpected errors. Incidents like this can be avoided by considering more edge cases when writing the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data was obtained by web scraping gasbuddy.com, which is a website where anyone can upload data. This source can be inaccurate and unreliable sometimes. Better sources can be used to improve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must have been more statistical tools that can be used for analysis. More exhaustive research on them could offer more information about the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make prediction, apart from a larger amount of dataset and a well-modeled algorithm, a good understanding of economics can be important. Generalizing patterns as discussed in the results section is important, but an educated guess may also come from an existing the economic model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a learning experience, this project enhances my software programming skills, which I don’t usually learn from my EE curriculum. This was also my first time using SQL database, which I found is a useful tool with a steep learning curve. Finally, as of the closing phase, I came to realize that I did not know enough statistical and economical tools to understand the data comprehensively, and therefore I became interested and motivated to learn them along my study.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>A Chiptune Music System with OPL2 and Reality Adlib Tracker</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20191202-a-chiptune-music-system-with-opl2-and-reality-adlib-tracker" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2019-12-02:/articles/20191202-a-chiptune-music-system-with-opl2-and-reality-adlib-tracker</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found at my GitHub &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/opl2-chiptune"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the project is to build a system with the old-school electronic components that plays Chiptune music, as well as composing the music with compatible software. This is a project for the class Japanese Music Online …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found at my GitHub &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/opl2-chiptune"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the project is to build a system with the old-school electronic components that plays Chiptune music, as well as composing the music with compatible software. This is a project for the class Japanese Music Online during Fall 2019 semester.  Dr. Kazuaki Shiota was really nice to let me do this for the final project of the class. The project helped me understand the theory behind Chiptune Music from a musical and engineering standpoint. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="how-chiptune-music-works"&gt;How Chiptune Music Works&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#how-chiptune-music-works" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="beeper-speakers"&gt;Beeper Speakers&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#beeper-speakers" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In embedded systems, I have experimented generating music made by square-waves with a piezoelectric speaker. The tone of the music is adjusted by the frequency of the square waves, as a method called “Frequency Modulation (FM)”. Such “beeper speaker” system is how early home computers generate sounds, except the CPU also handles other processes as a normal PC does (Figure 1). Different tones can be played by varying the frequency of the square waves, however, it requires all of the CPU’s run-time to implement advanced sound of music. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="fm-synthesizer"&gt;FM Synthesizer&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#fm-synthesizer" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve this issue, computers in the early 1980’s use dedicated sound chip (Figure 2), which is the early form of the sound cards in today’s computers. Except for taking the processing load away from the CPU, this method also creates possibility to develop more advanced sound generation and even synthesis. Three examples can be examined as examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/fm-synth.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 1 (Left) - Non-Dedicated Sound Chip; Figure 2 (Right) - Dedicated Sound Chip &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="nintendo-entertainment-system-nes"&gt;Nintendo Entertainment System (NES)&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#nintendo-entertainment-system-nes" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound chip in NES is able to generate five channels, each of which features different types of waveforms (Figure 3). Channel #1 and #2 gives square waves, Channel #3 gives triangle waves, Channel #4 gives noise and Channel #5 is PCM sample, which modulate pre-recorded sound waves. Though the tone can be different, this method makes the music sounds like being played by the same set of instruments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/NES.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 3 - NES Sound Chip &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="commodore-64"&gt;Commodore 64&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#commodore-64" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commodore uses a different approach to synthesize music. The chip has 3 channels, each of which can produce waveforms among square, triangle and sawtooth wave (Figure 4) . Initially, engineers assign used to assign one waveform to a channel and write the tone associated with the wave. This seems inferior to the NES system as it only has 3 channels, despite that the combination of the waveforms can be variable. However, later engineers realized that waveform can be reassigned to channels on the fly, which has opened a great amount of variability to the music. This methods have been proved successful and extended to the next generation of sound card in PC. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/C64.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 4 - Commodore 64 Sound Chip &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="adlibsound-blaster-card"&gt;Adlib/Sound-Blaster Card&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#adlibsound-blaster-card" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an improved version of the Commodor 64 sound chip, the Adlib Sound Card is used in the later IBM PC. The Card is replaced with Sound Blaster later due to the market loss,  but the key component - YM3812 FM Operator chip is used in both boards. This chip is considered the foundation of computer music on IBM PC for a decade, and can even found in some Yamaha electronic piano keyboards. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YM3812&lt;/strong&gt; is an Frequency Modulation Operator Type-L2 (OPL2) integrated chip that can simultaneously generate 9 channels of different types of waveforms. Since this chip was widely used in early computer systems, there are still supporting documents, software, and projects related to it, so it has been determined as the core of this project as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hardware-setup"&gt;Hardware Setup&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#hardware-setup" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 is the hardware setup of the system in block diagram. The music file stored in the SD card is read by the microcontroller (μC). The OPL2 chip uses 4-line bus for control signal and 8-line bus for data transfer. To reduce the load on the microcontroller, the data is sent in serial first to a shift register, and then transmitted to the OPL2 chip after the conversion. The digital output of the FM operation is thereafter transferred to a DAC, whose analog output is amplified to become the eventual sound that can be played by a speaker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/block.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 5 - Block Diagram &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detailed schematic of the system is in Figure 9. It is made in KiCAD, a free CAD software for PCB design. In order to reduce the cross-talk and noise of the system, it was decided to make the system into a PCB. After a few hours’ layout design, the final version of the board (Figure 10) is submitted to OSH Park Proto-PCB Service. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The KiCAD files are available in the GitHub repository attached at the begining of the post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/schematic.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 6 - Circuit Schematic &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/pcb.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 7 - PCB Demo &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="software"&gt;Software&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#software" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software portion of the project consists of the controlling program on the microcontroller and the music composing software. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the microcontroller is determined to be Arduino Uno as it’s the most available option, the controlling program is written in C++ in Arduino IDE. In addition to an external OPL2 library that handles the communication protocol, libraries such as SD and SPI are included too for the SD module board. The Arduino code is available in the GitHub repository attached at the end of the post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reality Adlib Tacker II (Figure 11) is the software for me to compose the music. It is a music tracker with an old-school GUI but an extensive documentation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-chiptune/reality.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 8 - Reality Adlib Tracker &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="result-demonstration"&gt;Result Demonstration&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#result-demonstration" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the PCB design is manufactured, an alpha prototype is made on a breadboard, in order to test the functionality of the design. The video below demonstrates the alpha system playing a sample test music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rFG_2tbkUiI" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that the design is functional, the next phase was a hardware and software upgrade. Hardware-wise, the PCB was sent to the manufacturer and assembled later. Software-wise, a specific piece of music was chosen to be recreated with the Tracker by myself. The video below is the final version of the system, playing Megalovania from the game Undertale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="summary-and-recommendation"&gt;Summary and Recommendation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary-and-recommendation" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this multi-disciplinary project was not only successful but also meaningful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a music standpoint, I learned how early electronic/computer music works and experienced the same method of composing it as the early 1900s game designed did. I am amazed too by the ingenuity of them making a variety of music with such limited system. Luckily, chiptune (or 8-bit) music remains as a featured style of music nowadays, which, to some extent, pays a tribute to those who used to work on electronic music composition. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an electrical engineering standpoint, this is a thorough embedded system engineering project starting from an idea, to research, design, assembly, testing and eventually realization. A lot of effort was used in designing the circuit, which is one of reasons of deciding to make a PCB. I also gained experience in audio engineering, such as signal amplification and reducing noise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, some recommendations are listed for future improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of using Arduino Uno board, the system can be simpler by integrating Teensy board into the PCB. Thus, the system will become an actual sound card. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The OPL2 library was used, but not fully understood yet. Reading through the code may help understanding the theories of operation even more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The process of loading the sound file in the SD card is time-consuming. It can be improved by developing a direct interface with PC and the system. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>Mathematical Steady State Analysis by Plotting in Python</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20191021-mathematical-steady-state-analysis-by-plotting-in-python" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2019-10-21:/articles/20191021-mathematical-steady-state-analysis-by-plotting-in-python</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/nullclineplot"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a whole project, but actually part of the final project on a class called Math Modelling. For the project, my friend, Wayne Stegner (Computer Engineering Undergraduate at UC), and I were supposed to model an age-based predation and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/nullclineplot"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a whole project, but actually part of the final project on a class called Math Modelling. For the project, my friend, Wayne Stegner (Computer Engineering Undergraduate at UC), and I were supposed to model an age-based predation and analyze the behavior of the model. This article will not focus on how we approached the model mathematically, but rather how we used Python to plot the model for the steady state analysis to avoid solving for multi-variable differential equations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#background" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model was reduced to two equations in (Eq 1), where u and v are independent variables. &lt;strong&gt;Steady state&lt;/strong&gt; is where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{du}{dt}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{dv}{dt}\)&lt;/span&gt; are both 0. However, it can be difficult to solve by setting both equations to 0, so we can use nullclines of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{du}{dt}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{dv}{dt}\)&lt;/span&gt; instead. &lt;strong&gt;Nullcline&lt;/strong&gt; of a variable is the plot where the derivative this variable over time is 0. Therefore, the intercept of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(u\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt; represents steady state. Moreover, a steady state can also be &lt;strong&gt;stable&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;unstable&lt;/strong&gt;. This is done by &lt;strong&gt;linear stability analysis&lt;/strong&gt;. In this specific model, it was found that the steady state is stable if the equation in Eq. 2 is positive; otherwise unstable. Thus, the discussion over steady state is around two questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does steady state exist in the given domain? How many of them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the steady state stable?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python script that plots the model is supposed to give a direct answer to these two questions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
\frac{d}{d\tau} v = B u - v - D v (u+v) - P v \\
\frac{d}{d\tau} u = v - u (u+v) - Q u
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: right"&gt; Differential Equations of the Model (Eq 1) &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
D = (- 1 - Du - 2Dv - P)(-2u - v - Q) - (1 - u)(B - D v)
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: right"&gt; Stability Criterion (Eq 2) &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id="methodology"&gt;Methodology&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#methodology" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two differential equations in Eq. 1 are both functions of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(u\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt;, so by plotting the u-nullcline and v-nullcline on a &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(u\)&lt;/span&gt;-vs-&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinate plane, steady state is where the two nullclines intercept. If they ever intercept, steady state exist, and how many intercepts dictates the number of steady states. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt; variable in Eq. 2 is also a function of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(u\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt;, but now the criterion is its sign, or an inequality between 0. On one hand, plugging in a steady state expression that is already complicated is hard, on the other hand, graphically, such inequality separates the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(u-v\)&lt;/span&gt; plane into two areas, positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt; and negative &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt;. Therefore, a contour map of this &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt; function can be superimposed onto the two nullcline plot. If their intercept is located in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D&amp;gt;0\)&lt;/span&gt; region, the steady state is stable; otherwise unstable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="result"&gt;Result&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#result" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plotting was successful. We were able to test the steady states by setting different external parameters (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(B\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt;) and draw conclusions out of the testings without math-heavy calculations. Some example results are shown figures below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-nullclineplot/plt1.webp"/&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-nullclineplot/plt2.webp"/&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-nullclineplot/plt3.webp"/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-i-learned-from-this"&gt;What I learned from this&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-i-learned-from-this" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Math sometimes can be hard and time-consuming for engineers. Luckily, with adequate programming skills, computer plotting can be helpful, making math analysis experimental. Such implementation, however, requires a clear vision on the math itself as well as an appropriate way to visualize the data. For our math modelling project, we were able to identify the two questions the analysis is based upon, and create a good method to answer both in one plot, making the program useful to the analysis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For questions regarding the program or the math model itself, please contact me using the sidebar or contact Wayne Stegner at stegnewe@mail.uc.edu.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>Using Google Calendar API to Auto-Create Tutoring Events</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20191021-using-google-calendar-api-to-auto-create-tutoring-events" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2019-10-21:/articles/20191021-using-google-calendar-api-to-auto-create-tutoring-events</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/TutorCal"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a project I started personally since March 2019 when I worked as a peer tutor at UC Tutoring Center (previously called Learning Commons). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="motivation"&gt;Motivation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#motivation" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Peer Tutoring works at UC is that students schedule appointments with me, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The source of the project can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/TutorCal"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a project I started personally since March 2019 when I worked as a peer tutor at UC Tutoring Center (previously called Learning Commons). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="motivation"&gt;Motivation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#motivation" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Peer Tutoring works at UC is that students schedule appointments with me, and I get email notification when they do so. TutorTrac is a system where students schedule appointments, and I see my appointments beforehand. An example of how the system looks is shown in Figure 1. However, though being a stable system maintained since 2011, TutorTrac has some inconvenient features&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is hard for me to navigate when I use my phone to look at my schedule&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For every event, it shows Last name first, but we usually refer to students’ first name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It only shows the class code of the assisting course instead of full name, making me hard to identify the class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This encourages me to develop my own method of seeing the schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/tutortrac.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 1 - TutorTrac System &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design"&gt;Design&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#design" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system reads the email notification of incoming tutoring appointments, scrapes the necessary information, and pushes it to my Google calendar in a better format. Thus I can see my schedule directly from the calendar widget of my phone (Android). Ideally it should scan the email notifications every 10-30 minutes and automatically generate events without being monitored. Additional good-to-have feature is that it will also store the appointment info at local, and try to match everyday’s schedule reminder sent from TutorTrac. Later it was found this part was hard to implement given the time, so it was deserted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="design-diagram"&gt;Design diagram&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#design-diagram" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/design.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 2 - Design Diagram &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="reading-uc-email-notifications"&gt;Reading UC Email Notifications&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#reading-uc-email-notifications" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notification received from TutorTrac follows a specific format (Figure 3). Therefore it is viable to hard-code the format into the program, making the scraping info method easier. Additionally, considering UC email is my most important mail address, as well as the fact that getting around UC server is hard and possibly not allowed, I created a rule at my UC mailbox to automatically forward any emails from TutorTrac to a gmail account I created for this project. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/email.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 3 - TutorTrac Email Notif &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="main-program"&gt;Main Program&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#main-program" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program is made up of three python scripts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;email_read.py&lt;/code&gt;: contains functions that reads email from Gmail account and scrape appointment info. Email interface is through imaplib module. Additionally, there is a csv look-up table, where the program can find the matching full name of the class from the course code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;google_cal.py&lt;/code&gt;: contains functions that pushes the appointment info to my Google calendar. This script is inspired by an article on Google site &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/calendar/quickstart/python"&gt;Google Calendar API Python Quickstart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;controller.py&lt;/code&gt;: uses the two modules and sets up the logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="hardware-implementation"&gt;Hardware Implementation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#hardware-implementation" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project does not requires too much in hardware except for the ability to run Python scripts and Internet accessibility. Therefore a Raspberry Pi 3 Model B (Figure 4) was used to implement the design. VNC Viewer is used to remote control the machine wirelessly from other computers. Raspbian with Kernel verion 4.14 was installed on the board, where it was found that there is a Scheduling tool (Figure 5) that lets a command run every period of time. This can also be done by hard-coding in CRON, which is the core of scheduling tool (i.e. scheduling is a GUI of CRON). Detail info about using CRON or scheduling tool see /CRONtest/note.txt on GitHub repo. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/rpi.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 4 - Raspberry Pi 3 in Operation &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/rpi.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 5 - Cron Task Setup &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4 id="long-term-management-and-maintenance"&gt;Long-Term Management and Maintenance&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#long-term-management-and-maintenance" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sure the program runs completely without errors stopping the process, I changed the script so that the error message will show in log file while the erroneous part is passed. Using &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module, the code also logs important stages in the operations (Figure 6). I also coded parts where the Internet is used to push/pull data to allow 99 retries, reducing the odds of getting bad connections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/log.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 6 - Cron Task Setup &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="results"&gt;Results&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#results" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was successful. It helped me manage my tutoring schedule over the last month of the semester. I was able to see who scheduled what class at my phone easily. Figure 8 is a side-by-side comparison between TutorTrac and how it turns out in my Google calendar. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/project-tutorcal/gcal.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt; Figure 7 - TutorTrac schedule (left, yellow blocks) vs Google Calendar (right, blue blocks) &lt;/small&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-i-learned-from-the-project"&gt;What I Learned From the Project&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-i-learned-from-the-project" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access emails in Python with imaplib&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create Google calendar events with Google API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use logging to maintain a constantly running program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a hardware environment (Raspberry Pi) and method to support a mini-server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="future-recommendations"&gt;Future Recommendations&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#future-recommendations" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushing events can be easy, but retrieving them from my calendar may be hard. For future implementation, it will be good to have an additional module to retrieve the events, check with the local record, thus making sure the schedule is correct. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>College Third Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20190901-college-third-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2019-09-01:/articles/20190901-college-third-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;After two semesters of Co-op in Cleveland, I was back to UC for two academic semesters. In contrast to the first year when I was trying to adapt to college and the environment, I was able to enjoy the process of studying Electrical Engineering during this third year in UC …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;After two semesters of Co-op in Cleveland, I was back to UC for two academic semesters. In contrast to the first year when I was trying to adapt to college and the environment, I was able to enjoy the process of studying Electrical Engineering during this third year in UC, not only because there were a lot more major-targeted courses, but also because I have experienced how Electrical Engineering was needed in the actual industry during Co-op. In this year-in review, I will mainly discuss around Co-op and EE classes I have taken over the last year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="co-op"&gt;Co-op&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#co-op" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first Co-op was at Jergens in Cleveland. Jergens is a manufacturing company that makes mechanical lifting materials, work-holding fixtures and fasteners for special uses. As a Co-op, I spent half of my time working as a machine supervisor, who oversaw daily job operations on a laser engraving machine and an automatic assembly machine. On the other hand, I was also a project manager for an automatic safety system on a grinder machine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student who had never been to a manufacturing shop before, I have had a special experience. I got to see the operational structure the company has maintained to keep thousands of parts manufactured every day, and as an electrical engineer who worked in that context, there are aspects that I have never considered, but is critical to the industry. For example, a hardware emergency-stop device such as a button that literally cut the electric line, is preferred than a software E-stop button that resets a logical variable to 0 in the program. I also learned safety regulations like OSCIA rules, electrical standards on drawing and color coding, as well as project management skills. Apart from that, my programming skill helped me create some useful software tool that increases the efficiency in the job transferring process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
You can also read more technical details of my Co-op at &lt;a href="https://liu2z2.github.io/pro-exp.html"&gt;Professional Experience&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I enjoyed the project I was given, I have concluded that I was not suitable to manufacturing environments, due to the fact that I did not enjoy the machine supervising very much. The main reason was that I got tired easily watching the machine doing the same thing all the time. Therefore, I also found myself project-orientated, as I had tried hard to push the progress of the project even to overtime. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lesson was also valuable, though, as it helped me identify my desired working positions in the future, and thus pushed me to find a Co-op in another industry. Currently I am Co-oping in Ethicon, which is a company that prototypes medical surgery devices. After this semester of Co-op, I believe I will have another type of experience of electrical engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="classes"&gt;Classes&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#classes" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_1"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to UC, during the last two semesters, I have learned a lot more about electronics and signal processing. Electronics had taught me different implementations of hardware designs, which is the very foundation of all silicon-based devices. Signal processing, however, is a field where engineers cares more about the data incorporated inside the electronics devices. Electrical engineering is incomplete without either of them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semiconductor devices is another interesting class I had taken. The class focuses to a level even lower than electronics, and upon how the devices are made in a physics aspect, for example, how the electrons passes through the device under a specific voltage threshold. On the other hand, I also learned Python from a class, which later was found is the most useful programming language to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_1"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronics and signal processing introduced me to two different levels of electrical engineering. I have things to love and hate for both classes. Hopefully after this current Co-op, I am able to identify an area that I am most interested in, so that I can initiate my senior project to that area. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I have found that learning Python was extremely useful to my programming learning path. My interest in programming was also increased greatly since I learned the language. With this simple and powerful language, I was able to go through different projects given by classes and myself. In my [PROJECT] tab, I have showcased some projects over the last semester. I wish I could keep update this blog of project showcases, as it motivates me and recorded my progress in learning electrical engineering as well. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>College Second Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20180901-college-second-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2018-09-01:/articles/20180901-college-second-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;My second year of study at University of Cincinnati featured a successful job hunt for my first Co-op. Therefore for this year-in review I would like to reflect on my Co-op search experience. Some part overlaps with events happening last year, but in general the whole story concluded by the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;My second year of study at University of Cincinnati featured a successful job hunt for my first Co-op. Therefore for this year-in review I would like to reflect on my Co-op search experience. Some part overlaps with events happening last year, but in general the whole story concluded by the end of last year. The reflection includes a background involving my Co-op search, an overview of my Co-op search experience in chronological order, challenges that I encountered, lessons that I learned, and some suggestions I would like to give to employers who are reading my reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="initial-plan-on-academic-and-career-path"&gt;Initial Plan on Academic and Career Path&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#initial-plan-on-academic-and-career-path" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to concern about my Co-op during the second semester, knowing the fact that F1 visa students have limitations like CPT and OPT. I learned from my research that I have one year to work before graduation (CPT, curricular practical training), one year after graduation (OPT, optional practical training), and two-year extended OPT time for STEM students. This infers that I have one year in total allowed for Co-op, and three years allowed to work after graduation. However, one year only fills up to three Co-op semesters, and I am required to complete five to graduate, so I have three possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though OPT should be spent after graduation, it is viable to be used before graduation, but this also means I have less time of employment after graduation, which I plan to use to consider perusing another degree or applying working visa (H1B visa has the during of six years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching for a job outside USA is another solution. Apart from the fact that I can possibly find a position in my home country, UC also offers International Co-op Program (ICP) to Japan and Germany, which are the countries I would like to visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on campus in a research position does not count either CPT or OPT. Even though an undergraduate research student may not make large impact, but such experience working in a lab helps me to decide if I want to be in the academia field in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possible Co-op rotation starts at fall 2017 or spring 2018. Being aware that I lack both knowledge and technical skill compared to other students, I chose the later rotation plan. Fortunately, during last summer I participated in UC’s Protégé Undergraduate Research Program. By working in a research lab even before a Co-op, I gained a lot of useful knowledge and skills that I can put on my resume. It was also this experience that made me decide on which side of electrical engineering I want to choose for my career path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="co-op-search-experience"&gt;Co-op Search Experience&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#co-op-search-experience" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
Due to my interest in hardware more than software as an electrical engineer, the initial goal of my first Co-op goes into three ways: either engage in micro-electronic circuit design, or work on logic control systems, or explore more in the manufacturing industry. The ranking of companies on PAL system was based on the three goals. Though we were told to rank fifty companies “very interested” at first, I ranked ninety of them just in case. Those “very interested” companies receive my resume immediately. I had skim through all three hundred positions, and marked about a hundred positions as “somewhat interested.” Companies of this rank will not be sent with my resume, but since I was slightly interested in them, I could use them to create my second-trial ranking list later when the first trial ended a month later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Career fair at UC on September 14 was the first event I committed a lot to my Co-op search, during which I made connections with plenty of good companies in different industries including electronics, robotics, manufacturing, and even greenhouse systems. For the following days I had heard back from two companies, Company X and Y, who would like to interview me. Company X was a very famous company making micro-processing devices. Company Y was a relatively small company making medical surgery devices. Though the medical surgery devices interested me a lot, Company X is in the industry I had been longing for, and I believe would had more impact on my resume, so I was extremely excited to work for Company X. However, I was told Company X could not give me a final decision until the end of November. Thus, for the following two months I had been in an awkward scenario – I had to keep searching for other job because I was not sure if Company X would give me an offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During these two months I had interviewed with about ten more companies, but did not achieve any offer letters. At the middle of October, I also went back in PAL to rank fifty more positions. Jergens Inc, the company that I will Co-op for, was one of the fifty positions. At the middle of November, I decided to email Company X for the status of my application, when I eventually found I was not accepted. My mind at this time quickly told myself that there was no time to be depressed or disappointed, since there are very few days left to find a job. I emailed two professors whose research topic interested me, thinking that research lab position could also be an alternative option. It was at this time Tim, Supervisor of Jergens Inc, interviewed me. Being aware that this might be my last interview, I decided to perform with the same enthusiasm as before and hoped I could get their appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, Jergens ctually extended me an offer! They assigned me responsibilities related to my goal, so I quickly accepted an offer. Now I am already trying to find a housing in Cleveland and getting ready to work. That had made a successful ending of my Co-op search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#challenges" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
Throughout my whole semester of Co-op searching, there were a few difficulties I have faced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of my citizenship. Due to many reasons, companies, especially large ones, usually think of international students as employees with very low return for the company. Students like me therefore got blocked away at the first step of the hiring process. To solve this issue, on my resume I wrote down another line below my name, saying “international student with 3-year extension working time in USA after graduation (and possible 6 more years with working visa)” This will clarify my eligibility of working in America for companies who think the stated time is enough to benefit from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uncertain time scale of the hiring process. Different companies have different schedules for hiring. While some companies are able to tell me the final decision after a few days after the interview, other companies like Company X need much more time to proceed. Since I was looking forward to working at Company X very much, I decided to wait patiently for their response. In the meantime, however, I still needed to look for other companies because I was not hired yet. In addition, the idea that I might be employed by the famous Company X also affected me ranking other companies because I would have high expectation from other famous companies as well, therefore overlooking small companies that may also benefit me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of communication skills and experience. Since this is my first time looking for a job, I had no idea when I should follow up with companies after interview, and when I could expect to hear from them. Fortunately, this soft skill was gradually trained by having interview with companies after another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#lessons-learned" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through my rough semester of Co-op searching, I had learned several lessons that are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good to be hired by a company of interested field, but that does not mean to reject other industries, which may surprisingly interest me. Company Y, for example, is a company making medical surgery devices, which I initially thought will be boring to me. However, during the talk with them I was shown with several high-technology electronic devices such as ultrasonic cutting, so I realized that I may actually grow passion about what I will work on in Company Y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different companies when hiring Co-op students may have different expectations. While it is true that some companies may make students start from very easy jobs like documenting, other companies will expect their Co-op students contribute much to the think tank, which often occurs in R&amp;amp;D positions. Therefore, when I do research on a company before interview, apart from understanding their background, I should also try identifying their expectations on me before they tell me. In addition, employers also value differently. Typical large companies like Company X look for specific skills (like specific programming languages), Jergens, the company that eventually hired me, values my general passion on electronic devices and systems. Company Y was interested in my technical skills and electrical intuition. Interestingly, they did not give me an offer, but instead, asked me to apply to them again after I gained enough academic knowledge. Most likely, they valued a solid academic background more than what I outstood in my resume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fine to wait for a good company’s response, but I should also make a back-up plan. After I knew I was not accepted by Company X, I panicked and began to spam my resume to almost random companies on PAL. Fortunately, I was extended an offer by Jergens, but I would not be always that lucky. Now when I look back at the beginning of the semester, I may actually have a lot more chances to be hired by some interesting companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>Engineering Models TA Experience</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20171120-engineering-models-ta-experience" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2017-11-20:/articles/20171120-engineering-models-ta-experience</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Engineering Models is a mandatory freshman class for all engineering students at UC. It aims to train students&amp;rsquo; basic IT and programming skills by teaching them basic engineering uses of MATLAB and Excel. Around the two software, there are lectures teaching students fundamentals (for example, I/O statement, for/while …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Engineering Models is a mandatory freshman class for all engineering students at UC. It aims to train students&amp;rsquo; basic IT and programming skills by teaching them basic engineering uses of MATLAB and Excel. Around the two software, there are lectures teaching students fundamentals (for example, I/O statement, for/while loops, conditional statements, etc.) Students will finish a small project during each recitation session, where they encounter topics of different background (mechanical, chemical, electrical, etc.) and uses their learned skills to solve practical problems in a programming perspective. This is usually called “lab” as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the TA for the class, my main responsibility is to answer students’ questions, gives them hints, and check answers for their lab projects. I also did more work than normal TA because I used this as an Honors experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the 13-week lab sessions, I not only gained experience of instructing others with their programming instead of writing the code myself, but also practiced some teaching philosophy and methodology offered by Niki (Caroline Harrison), who is the student-wise supervisor for this pre-approved honors experience. Another thing that the experience made me realize is that different people write programs differently. This idea helps me to open myself to read others’ code as well as gives me the patience to help them debug their code, instead of telling people “your code does not work use mine.” They are important professional skills too especially when I need to work other co-workers during Co-op.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the semester, a final project required for Honors experience is to design a lab/homework that can be used to introduce a new concept or improve the existing content. My project is a lab whose topic is “Decimal to Binary Converter”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of technical skills, the lab helps students practice using I/O statements, conditional statement and loops, as well as beware students of the difference between strings and numbers in programming. In terms of the content, the lab teaches students how the binary number system, which is used in computers, can be easily transformed to decimal number system, which human is familiar with. Students will also understand how powerful the binary number system is, with the enhancement given by ingenious engineering design (such as the signed binary system).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the teaching process learned from Niki, I understood that new information needs to be given step by step rather than as a chunk. Therefore, I took it apart to three sections, Part A, B and C. Thus, students are able to understand the concept by fully practicing it inside each section, so that they are ready for another new piece of information in the next section. The screen shot below briefly shows how the program executes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/discuss-modelsTA.webp"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources of the program can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/models1ta"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>College First Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20170901-college-first-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2017-09-01:/articles/20170901-college-first-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I believe that every year that I had gone through gives me extraordinary change, especially this year. The academic year of 2016 – 2017 witnessed my first time going to university, living in America where foreign language is spoken, and being far away from home for four months long. Though thinking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I believe that every year that I had gone through gives me extraordinary change, especially this year. The academic year of 2016 – 2017 witnessed my first time going to university, living in America where foreign language is spoken, and being far away from home for four months long. Though thinking that the combination of those firsts would be even tougher, my first year in University of Cincinnati in USA was actually exciting and fruitful. I would like to detail my first year in the following sections with a “what? so what? now what?” model. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="adaption"&gt;Adaption&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#adaption" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language and culture shock is absolutely the first challenge. Even though I had already been fluent in English, it still took me a while to be able to communicate as a native speaker due to the ignorance of certain vocabulary or conventions in American language and culture. For example, the staff in sales business’s front line are mostly called “cashier”, but in banks they are called “tellers.” Another example is that customers are supposed to go to a staff in the clothes store for a fitting room, and are probably asked about the items to try. The staff can also help the customers to hold the clothes that they do not want to buy anymore. Yet in my home country, going to fitting room and putting away clothes are both self-service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response of this difference from my old “common sense”, and to avoid embarrassment of making bad choices, I had developed my ability to observe and quickly learn, and I found myself benefiting from this method a lot. In fact, I could tell that I am able to learn at least one word every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolution theory claims that even one favorable feature could help an organism or species to adapt the environment and eventually win the natural selection. I would like to say, this feature of mine is the adept ability of observation and quick learning. For my second year and probably future years at UC, I believe that if I utilize and hone this ability further in academic study, my proficiency in learning would be maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="education"&gt;Education&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#education" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_1"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not arguable that I, as a Chinese student, do have a better understanding of basic math and science at the first year of college, since I have accumulated a lot of experience in those from middle school and high school. I believe this wide scope of experience ranging from math, biology, chemistry and physics will offer me more inspirations in the later engineering study, for the fact that engineering is the combination of sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking back to my major specifically, I am actually short of a significant amount of knowledge that I am supposed to have as an electrical engineer. Programming, as an example, is the field that I know nothing about before the first semester. Theoretical circuit analysis is my strength, yet this gives me little advantage because operational circuit and coding have been crucial in current electrical technology. Therefore, I began to boost myself into program learning by reading textbooks, working on self-designed projects as well as making friends with people in the same major and computer engineering major. The methods were efficient. Finishing a C++ project by myself is not a worry anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_1"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a time I asked a senior electrical engineering student what is the most important advantage as an electrical engineer, and he answered GPA and the ability to code. Consequently, in the second year at UC, my effort will be onto these two elements. There may be very few situations where I can use my past knowledge, for later in the second year the classes will be major specific and new to me, so I must study harder. I will also maintain extra effort on learning programming. That will give me a better understanding in operational circuit too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="connections"&gt;Connections&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#connections" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_2"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_2" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before entering in America, I was determined to try going beyond my comfort zone, and especially not to tag along with Chinese people, in order to adapt American culture as soon as possible. It was difficult at first, and sometimes awkward since I did not understand their jokes or “memes,” and I made unexpected reactions due to misunderstanding, yet the more I tried, the more I was able to express myself and follow their conversations. Eventually in the second semester, five other classmates and I became a group who often studied together, had food together and hanged out together on weekends. Now I have to say, apart from my roommate, my closest friends are all Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_2"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_2" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding all the connections and friends that I have made, I feel very grateful to the Learning Community that I participated in and also my peer leader, whose younger brother is actually my best friend, so that I could learn from smarter people and achieve self-improvement. Yet speaking of self-improvement, there is no better people than older engineering students, who have been through my stage and has the best advice for me. So my future plan in respect of connection is to build more connections with older students. Student organizations are one of the best resources, and I will start from joining some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="future"&gt;Future&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#future" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_3"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_3" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interest in artificial intelligence and reverse-engineering-the-brain made me choose electrical engineering. For the first year of college study, I have confirmed that this is a right path for me. I felt lucky to know about the ACCEND Program, which could help me to achieve my passion full-heartedly. However, it is indeed difficult to have a clear vision of the future as an international student, who has to consider such factors as family (not able to go home for more than three months), academics (whether to pursue master or doctor degree), employment (possibility to obtain a job offer after graduation) and immigration policy (limited time to work as a student).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​#### Now what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware of the fact that these factors are unavoidable, I decided to put my passion away for now and cope with other obstacles. For now as a mere second year undergraduate, I will keep my interest activated, but meanwhile care about upcoming issues first, for example, finding a coop or becoming active in student organizations. Struggling for everything is inevitable as an international student, so my dream for now is to maintain a good grit and keep improving myself in every aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="emotional-development"&gt;Emotional Development&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#emotional-development" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_4"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_4" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I admitted introvert might be my personality, I found myself more friendly and open to others since I came into USA. Due to the conventions in China, I used to never say hello to people that I meet in the street, but it becomes a very normal thing here. At first I just responded as a respect, but later I became willing to say good morning to every person that I see. Additionally, sharing my feelings and stories to others used to be a rare thing, but now I can do that even with a stranger that I meet in the shuttle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_3"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_3" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I know that is a good feature in American culture, I want other students know about it too. At some time when I have a chance to meet with freshman coming from China, I want them to know that American people do not hold racial discrimination, but instead, they might be kinder than Chinese people in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="feelings-about-myself"&gt;Feelings About Myself&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#feelings-about-myself" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_5"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_5" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gateway to Honors impressed me most of the topic on strengths. It was the first time that I was told about my strengths by other people thoroughly. My top five strengths are learner, futuristic, individualism, focus and intellection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​#### Now what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utilizing these strengths are my next step. I believe that the five elements can help me to achieve my goal in the fastest way. I also believe that I can further define my passion and my role in the community with the guidance of these five words.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>Protege Undergraduate Research Reflection</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20160901-protege-undergraduate-research-reflection" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2016-09-01:/articles/20160901-protege-undergraduate-research-reflection</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During Protégé Undergraduate Research Program, I worked in Dr. Rashmi Jha’s MIND lab on a project “Electrical Simulation of Neural Signals”. The program lasted four months, during which I researched on this topic as a full-time research student. For most of my time of research, I read books and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During Protégé Undergraduate Research Program, I worked in Dr. Rashmi Jha’s MIND lab on a project “Electrical Simulation of Neural Signals”. The program lasted four months, during which I researched on this topic as a full-time research student. For most of my time of research, I read books and literature, took notes, conducted experiment in the lab, collected data, analyzed the data and crafted my own design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience had teached me a lot of academic knowledge that I am about to learn in the incoming years (MOSFETs, amplifiers, microcontrollers, SPICE simulations, etc.), as well as some hands-on skills such as using different measuring instruments and soldering. In addition, this was my first time being an actual researcher in a lab so I have built a concept what it feels like to be in academia. My lab colleague were kind and patient to explain things I did not know. Despite their eagerness to accomplish their goal, one must finish this job on his/her own. This also involves the awareness of intellectual properties. I also learned effective ways to deliver information to different kinds of audience, for example, writing documentation and make presentation in a symposium. On the other hand, by studying on the concept of neuromorphic computing and trying to understand what other lab members have been doing, I have a general idea of how current technology has advanced and how I can participate into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to present my poster as a sample work of this experience. This summarizes in detail what I learned, what I wanted to do and what I accomplished. It is self-explanatory, informative and targeted to general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly I hope this experience will help me clarify my academic interests and pave my way in the future. I might ask Dr. Jha to include me in her lab again in the incoming semesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/discuss-protege.webp"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry></feed>