<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Liu's ePortfolio - Discussion</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/feeds/discussion.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://liu2z2.github.io/</id><updated>2022-11-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Spring 2021 Remark</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20221106-spring-2021-remark" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2022-11-06:/articles/20221106-spring-2021-remark</id><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="discussion"></category></entry><entry><title>Art/Neuroscience Combined Honors Seminar Reflection</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20200617-artneuroscience-combined-honors-seminar-reflection" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2020-06-17:/articles/20200617-artneuroscience-combined-honors-seminar-reflection</id><summary type="html">
&lt;h3 id="class-description"&gt;Class Description&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#class-description" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARTE3041/NS3041: From Neurons to Picasso: How and Why the Brain Makes Art
Offered in Spring Semester 2020
Instructed by Dr. Kris Holland and Dr. Ilya Vilinsky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="reflection-on-class"&gt;Reflection on Class&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#reflection-on-class" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineering student whose research project is related to Brain Computer Interface (BCI), I initially took this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;h3 id="class-description"&gt;Class Description&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#class-description" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARTE3041/NS3041: From Neurons to Picasso: How and Why the Brain Makes Art
Offered in Spring Semester 2020
Instructed by Dr. Kris Holland and Dr. Ilya Vilinsky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="reflection-on-class"&gt;Reflection on Class&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#reflection-on-class" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineering student whose research project is related to Brain Computer Interface (BCI), I initially took this seminar to learn the insights about the brain in other disciples. Dr. Holland and Dr. Vilinsky instructed the course well by giving us their expertise, motivating us to think and being welcome to discussion without any judgement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class was conducted by alternate lecture and discussion sessions with a few lab sessions that enhanced the learning experience. Different topics were covered under the discipline of art and neuroscience, including sight mechanism, neuroplasticity, evolution of art, memory, etc. We read class materials that were posted online, then reflect on them in the form of weekly writing assignments (WWA). Since the class partially falls under the study of art, we were also encouraged to take class notes on sketch books rather than ruled notebooks, and embody as much as drawing as possible to illustrate our thoughts. I especially appreciate the fact that other professors were invited in class to participate in discussion on their special research areas. They provided us even more perspectives on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, at the second half of the semester, the class schedule was disoriented by the pandemic. Class material was still posted on weekly basis, but the majority of the time I spent on the class at home was about the final project. The requirement of the final project was broad, so long as it is related to art and (or) neuroscience. At that time, I was learning machine learning (ML) and taking a class on digital image processing, so I decided to work on a project that imitates art styles and interprets them from a programming standpoint. Though the implementation was hard as I was new to ML, I finished it by the deadline with good results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the class itself, it was a meaningful and enjoyable experience, and I believe that it could have been even better if the second half of the semester went as planned. I definitely recommend this course to other students under any major, and I wish this class could continue for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="final-project-showcase"&gt;Final Project Showcase&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#final-project-showcase" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" height="600" src="/ViewerJS/#../extra/HS_final_project.pdf" style="width:100%;" webkitallowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>College Third Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20190901-college-third-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2019-09-01:/articles/20190901-college-third-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;After two semesters of Co-op in Cleveland, I was back to UC for two academic semesters. In contrast to the first year when I was trying to adapt to college and the environment, I was able to enjoy the process of studying Electrical Engineering during this third year in UC …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;After two semesters of Co-op in Cleveland, I was back to UC for two academic semesters. In contrast to the first year when I was trying to adapt to college and the environment, I was able to enjoy the process of studying Electrical Engineering during this third year in UC, not only because there were a lot more major-targeted courses, but also because I have experienced how Electrical Engineering was needed in the actual industry during Co-op. In this year-in review, I will mainly discuss around Co-op and EE classes I have taken over the last year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="co-op"&gt;Co-op&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#co-op" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first Co-op was at Jergens in Cleveland. Jergens is a manufacturing company that makes mechanical lifting materials, work-holding fixtures and fasteners for special uses. As a Co-op, I spent half of my time working as a machine supervisor, who oversaw daily job operations on a laser engraving machine and an automatic assembly machine. On the other hand, I was also a project manager for an automatic safety system on a grinder machine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student who had never been to a manufacturing shop before, I have had a special experience. I got to see the operational structure the company has maintained to keep thousands of parts manufactured every day, and as an electrical engineer who worked in that context, there are aspects that I have never considered, but is critical to the industry. For example, a hardware emergency-stop device such as a button that literally cut the electric line, is preferred than a software E-stop button that resets a logical variable to 0 in the program. I also learned safety regulations like OSCIA rules, electrical standards on drawing and color coding, as well as project management skills. Apart from that, my programming skill helped me create some useful software tool that increases the efficiency in the job transferring process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
You can also read more technical details of my Co-op at &lt;a href="https://liu2z2.github.io/pro-exp.html"&gt;Professional Experience&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I enjoyed the project I was given, I have concluded that I was not suitable to manufacturing environments, due to the fact that I did not enjoy the machine supervising very much. The main reason was that I got tired easily watching the machine doing the same thing all the time. Therefore, I also found myself project-orientated, as I had tried hard to push the progress of the project even to overtime. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lesson was also valuable, though, as it helped me identify my desired working positions in the future, and thus pushed me to find a Co-op in another industry. Currently I am Co-oping in Ethicon, which is a company that prototypes medical surgery devices. After this semester of Co-op, I believe I will have another type of experience of electrical engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="classes"&gt;Classes&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#classes" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_1"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to UC, during the last two semesters, I have learned a lot more about electronics and signal processing. Electronics had taught me different implementations of hardware designs, which is the very foundation of all silicon-based devices. Signal processing, however, is a field where engineers cares more about the data incorporated inside the electronics devices. Electrical engineering is incomplete without either of them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semiconductor devices is another interesting class I had taken. The class focuses to a level even lower than electronics, and upon how the devices are made in a physics aspect, for example, how the electrons passes through the device under a specific voltage threshold. On the other hand, I also learned Python from a class, which later was found is the most useful programming language to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_1"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronics and signal processing introduced me to two different levels of electrical engineering. I have things to love and hate for both classes. Hopefully after this current Co-op, I am able to identify an area that I am most interested in, so that I can initiate my senior project to that area. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I have found that learning Python was extremely useful to my programming learning path. My interest in programming was also increased greatly since I learned the language. With this simple and powerful language, I was able to go through different projects given by classes and myself. In my [PROJECT] tab, I have showcased some projects over the last semester. I wish I could keep update this blog of project showcases, as it motivates me and recorded my progress in learning electrical engineering as well. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>College Second Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20180901-college-second-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2018-09-01:/articles/20180901-college-second-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;My second year of study at University of Cincinnati featured a successful job hunt for my first Co-op. Therefore for this year-in review I would like to reflect on my Co-op search experience. Some part overlaps with events happening last year, but in general the whole story concluded by the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;My second year of study at University of Cincinnati featured a successful job hunt for my first Co-op. Therefore for this year-in review I would like to reflect on my Co-op search experience. Some part overlaps with events happening last year, but in general the whole story concluded by the end of last year. The reflection includes a background involving my Co-op search, an overview of my Co-op search experience in chronological order, challenges that I encountered, lessons that I learned, and some suggestions I would like to give to employers who are reading my reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="initial-plan-on-academic-and-career-path"&gt;Initial Plan on Academic and Career Path&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#initial-plan-on-academic-and-career-path" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to concern about my Co-op during the second semester, knowing the fact that F1 visa students have limitations like CPT and OPT. I learned from my research that I have one year to work before graduation (CPT, curricular practical training), one year after graduation (OPT, optional practical training), and two-year extended OPT time for STEM students. This infers that I have one year in total allowed for Co-op, and three years allowed to work after graduation. However, one year only fills up to three Co-op semesters, and I am required to complete five to graduate, so I have three possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though OPT should be spent after graduation, it is viable to be used before graduation, but this also means I have less time of employment after graduation, which I plan to use to consider perusing another degree or applying working visa (H1B visa has the during of six years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching for a job outside USA is another solution. Apart from the fact that I can possibly find a position in my home country, UC also offers International Co-op Program (ICP) to Japan and Germany, which are the countries I would like to visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on campus in a research position does not count either CPT or OPT. Even though an undergraduate research student may not make large impact, but such experience working in a lab helps me to decide if I want to be in the academia field in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possible Co-op rotation starts at fall 2017 or spring 2018. Being aware that I lack both knowledge and technical skill compared to other students, I chose the later rotation plan. Fortunately, during last summer I participated in UC’s Protégé Undergraduate Research Program. By working in a research lab even before a Co-op, I gained a lot of useful knowledge and skills that I can put on my resume. It was also this experience that made me decide on which side of electrical engineering I want to choose for my career path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="co-op-search-experience"&gt;Co-op Search Experience&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#co-op-search-experience" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
Due to my interest in hardware more than software as an electrical engineer, the initial goal of my first Co-op goes into three ways: either engage in micro-electronic circuit design, or work on logic control systems, or explore more in the manufacturing industry. The ranking of companies on PAL system was based on the three goals. Though we were told to rank fifty companies “very interested” at first, I ranked ninety of them just in case. Those “very interested” companies receive my resume immediately. I had skim through all three hundred positions, and marked about a hundred positions as “somewhat interested.” Companies of this rank will not be sent with my resume, but since I was slightly interested in them, I could use them to create my second-trial ranking list later when the first trial ended a month later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Career fair at UC on September 14 was the first event I committed a lot to my Co-op search, during which I made connections with plenty of good companies in different industries including electronics, robotics, manufacturing, and even greenhouse systems. For the following days I had heard back from two companies, Company X and Y, who would like to interview me. Company X was a very famous company making micro-processing devices. Company Y was a relatively small company making medical surgery devices. Though the medical surgery devices interested me a lot, Company X is in the industry I had been longing for, and I believe would had more impact on my resume, so I was extremely excited to work for Company X. However, I was told Company X could not give me a final decision until the end of November. Thus, for the following two months I had been in an awkward scenario – I had to keep searching for other job because I was not sure if Company X would give me an offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During these two months I had interviewed with about ten more companies, but did not achieve any offer letters. At the middle of October, I also went back in PAL to rank fifty more positions. Jergens Inc, the company that I will Co-op for, was one of the fifty positions. At the middle of November, I decided to email Company X for the status of my application, when I eventually found I was not accepted. My mind at this time quickly told myself that there was no time to be depressed or disappointed, since there are very few days left to find a job. I emailed two professors whose research topic interested me, thinking that research lab position could also be an alternative option. It was at this time Tim, Supervisor of Jergens Inc, interviewed me. Being aware that this might be my last interview, I decided to perform with the same enthusiasm as before and hoped I could get their appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, Jergens ctually extended me an offer! They assigned me responsibilities related to my goal, so I quickly accepted an offer. Now I am already trying to find a housing in Cleveland and getting ready to work. That had made a successful ending of my Co-op search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#challenges" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​
Throughout my whole semester of Co-op searching, there were a few difficulties I have faced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of my citizenship. Due to many reasons, companies, especially large ones, usually think of international students as employees with very low return for the company. Students like me therefore got blocked away at the first step of the hiring process. To solve this issue, on my resume I wrote down another line below my name, saying “international student with 3-year extension working time in USA after graduation (and possible 6 more years with working visa)” This will clarify my eligibility of working in America for companies who think the stated time is enough to benefit from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uncertain time scale of the hiring process. Different companies have different schedules for hiring. While some companies are able to tell me the final decision after a few days after the interview, other companies like Company X need much more time to proceed. Since I was looking forward to working at Company X very much, I decided to wait patiently for their response. In the meantime, however, I still needed to look for other companies because I was not hired yet. In addition, the idea that I might be employed by the famous Company X also affected me ranking other companies because I would have high expectation from other famous companies as well, therefore overlooking small companies that may also benefit me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of communication skills and experience. Since this is my first time looking for a job, I had no idea when I should follow up with companies after interview, and when I could expect to hear from them. Fortunately, this soft skill was gradually trained by having interview with companies after another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#lessons-learned" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through my rough semester of Co-op searching, I had learned several lessons that are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good to be hired by a company of interested field, but that does not mean to reject other industries, which may surprisingly interest me. Company Y, for example, is a company making medical surgery devices, which I initially thought will be boring to me. However, during the talk with them I was shown with several high-technology electronic devices such as ultrasonic cutting, so I realized that I may actually grow passion about what I will work on in Company Y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different companies when hiring Co-op students may have different expectations. While it is true that some companies may make students start from very easy jobs like documenting, other companies will expect their Co-op students contribute much to the think tank, which often occurs in R&amp;amp;D positions. Therefore, when I do research on a company before interview, apart from understanding their background, I should also try identifying their expectations on me before they tell me. In addition, employers also value differently. Typical large companies like Company X look for specific skills (like specific programming languages), Jergens, the company that eventually hired me, values my general passion on electronic devices and systems. Company Y was interested in my technical skills and electrical intuition. Interestingly, they did not give me an offer, but instead, asked me to apply to them again after I gained enough academic knowledge. Most likely, they valued a solid academic background more than what I outstood in my resume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fine to wait for a good company’s response, but I should also make a back-up plan. After I knew I was not accepted by Company X, I panicked and began to spam my resume to almost random companies on PAL. Fortunately, I was extended an offer by Jergens, but I would not be always that lucky. Now when I look back at the beginning of the semester, I may actually have a lot more chances to be hired by some interesting companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>Engineering Models TA Experience</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20171120-engineering-models-ta-experience" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2017-11-20:/articles/20171120-engineering-models-ta-experience</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Engineering Models is a mandatory freshman class for all engineering students at UC. It aims to train students&amp;rsquo; basic IT and programming skills by teaching them basic engineering uses of MATLAB and Excel. Around the two software, there are lectures teaching students fundamentals (for example, I/O statement, for/while …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Engineering Models is a mandatory freshman class for all engineering students at UC. It aims to train students&amp;rsquo; basic IT and programming skills by teaching them basic engineering uses of MATLAB and Excel. Around the two software, there are lectures teaching students fundamentals (for example, I/O statement, for/while loops, conditional statements, etc.) Students will finish a small project during each recitation session, where they encounter topics of different background (mechanical, chemical, electrical, etc.) and uses their learned skills to solve practical problems in a programming perspective. This is usually called “lab” as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the TA for the class, my main responsibility is to answer students’ questions, gives them hints, and check answers for their lab projects. I also did more work than normal TA because I used this as an Honors experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the 13-week lab sessions, I not only gained experience of instructing others with their programming instead of writing the code myself, but also practiced some teaching philosophy and methodology offered by Niki (Caroline Harrison), who is the student-wise supervisor for this pre-approved honors experience. Another thing that the experience made me realize is that different people write programs differently. This idea helps me to open myself to read others’ code as well as gives me the patience to help them debug their code, instead of telling people “your code does not work use mine.” They are important professional skills too especially when I need to work other co-workers during Co-op.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the semester, a final project required for Honors experience is to design a lab/homework that can be used to introduce a new concept or improve the existing content. My project is a lab whose topic is “Decimal to Binary Converter”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of technical skills, the lab helps students practice using I/O statements, conditional statement and loops, as well as beware students of the difference between strings and numbers in programming. In terms of the content, the lab teaches students how the binary number system, which is used in computers, can be easily transformed to decimal number system, which human is familiar with. Students will also understand how powerful the binary number system is, with the enhancement given by ingenious engineering design (such as the signed binary system).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the teaching process learned from Niki, I understood that new information needs to be given step by step rather than as a chunk. Therefore, I took it apart to three sections, Part A, B and C. Thus, students are able to understand the concept by fully practicing it inside each section, so that they are ready for another new piece of information in the next section. The screen shot below briefly shows how the program executes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/discuss-modelsTA.webp"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources of the program can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/liu2z2/models1ta"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>College First Year-In Review</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20170901-college-first-year-in-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2017-09-01:/articles/20170901-college-first-year-in-review</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I believe that every year that I had gone through gives me extraordinary change, especially this year. The academic year of 2016 – 2017 witnessed my first time going to university, living in America where foreign language is spoken, and being far away from home for four months long. Though thinking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I believe that every year that I had gone through gives me extraordinary change, especially this year. The academic year of 2016 – 2017 witnessed my first time going to university, living in America where foreign language is spoken, and being far away from home for four months long. Though thinking that the combination of those firsts would be even tougher, my first year in University of Cincinnati in USA was actually exciting and fruitful. I would like to detail my first year in the following sections with a “what? so what? now what?” model. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="adaption"&gt;Adaption&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#adaption" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language and culture shock is absolutely the first challenge. Even though I had already been fluent in English, it still took me a while to be able to communicate as a native speaker due to the ignorance of certain vocabulary or conventions in American language and culture. For example, the staff in sales business’s front line are mostly called “cashier”, but in banks they are called “tellers.” Another example is that customers are supposed to go to a staff in the clothes store for a fitting room, and are probably asked about the items to try. The staff can also help the customers to hold the clothes that they do not want to buy anymore. Yet in my home country, going to fitting room and putting away clothes are both self-service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response of this difference from my old “common sense”, and to avoid embarrassment of making bad choices, I had developed my ability to observe and quickly learn, and I found myself benefiting from this method a lot. In fact, I could tell that I am able to learn at least one word every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolution theory claims that even one favorable feature could help an organism or species to adapt the environment and eventually win the natural selection. I would like to say, this feature of mine is the adept ability of observation and quick learning. For my second year and probably future years at UC, I believe that if I utilize and hone this ability further in academic study, my proficiency in learning would be maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="education"&gt;Education&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#education" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_1"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not arguable that I, as a Chinese student, do have a better understanding of basic math and science at the first year of college, since I have accumulated a lot of experience in those from middle school and high school. I believe this wide scope of experience ranging from math, biology, chemistry and physics will offer me more inspirations in the later engineering study, for the fact that engineering is the combination of sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking back to my major specifically, I am actually short of a significant amount of knowledge that I am supposed to have as an electrical engineer. Programming, as an example, is the field that I know nothing about before the first semester. Theoretical circuit analysis is my strength, yet this gives me little advantage because operational circuit and coding have been crucial in current electrical technology. Therefore, I began to boost myself into program learning by reading textbooks, working on self-designed projects as well as making friends with people in the same major and computer engineering major. The methods were efficient. Finishing a C++ project by myself is not a worry anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_1"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_1" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a time I asked a senior electrical engineering student what is the most important advantage as an electrical engineer, and he answered GPA and the ability to code. Consequently, in the second year at UC, my effort will be onto these two elements. There may be very few situations where I can use my past knowledge, for later in the second year the classes will be major specific and new to me, so I must study harder. I will also maintain extra effort on learning programming. That will give me a better understanding in operational circuit too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="connections"&gt;Connections&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#connections" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_2"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_2" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before entering in America, I was determined to try going beyond my comfort zone, and especially not to tag along with Chinese people, in order to adapt American culture as soon as possible. It was difficult at first, and sometimes awkward since I did not understand their jokes or “memes,” and I made unexpected reactions due to misunderstanding, yet the more I tried, the more I was able to express myself and follow their conversations. Eventually in the second semester, five other classmates and I became a group who often studied together, had food together and hanged out together on weekends. Now I have to say, apart from my roommate, my closest friends are all Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_2"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_2" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding all the connections and friends that I have made, I feel very grateful to the Learning Community that I participated in and also my peer leader, whose younger brother is actually my best friend, so that I could learn from smarter people and achieve self-improvement. Yet speaking of self-improvement, there is no better people than older engineering students, who have been through my stage and has the best advice for me. So my future plan in respect of connection is to build more connections with older students. Student organizations are one of the best resources, and I will start from joining some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="future"&gt;Future&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#future" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_3"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_3" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interest in artificial intelligence and reverse-engineering-the-brain made me choose electrical engineering. For the first year of college study, I have confirmed that this is a right path for me. I felt lucky to know about the ACCEND Program, which could help me to achieve my passion full-heartedly. However, it is indeed difficult to have a clear vision of the future as an international student, who has to consider such factors as family (not able to go home for more than three months), academics (whether to pursue master or doctor degree), employment (possibility to obtain a job offer after graduation) and immigration policy (limited time to work as a student).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​#### Now what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware of the fact that these factors are unavoidable, I decided to put my passion away for now and cope with other obstacles. For now as a mere second year undergraduate, I will keep my interest activated, but meanwhile care about upcoming issues first, for example, finding a coop or becoming active in student organizations. Struggling for everything is inevitable as an international student, so my dream for now is to maintain a good grit and keep improving myself in every aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="emotional-development"&gt;Emotional Development&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#emotional-development" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_4"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_4" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I admitted introvert might be my personality, I found myself more friendly and open to others since I came into USA. Due to the conventions in China, I used to never say hello to people that I meet in the street, but it becomes a very normal thing here. At first I just responded as a respect, but later I became willing to say good morning to every person that I see. Additionally, sharing my feelings and stories to others used to be a rare thing, but now I can do that even with a stranger that I meet in the shuttle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="now-what_3"&gt;Now what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#now-what_3" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I know that is a good feature in American culture, I want other students know about it too. At some time when I have a chance to meet with freshman coming from China, I want them to know that American people do not hold racial discrimination, but instead, they might be kinder than Chinese people in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="feelings-about-myself"&gt;Feelings About Myself&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#feelings-about-myself" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="what-so-what_5"&gt;What? So what?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-so-what_5" title="Permanent link"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gateway to Honors impressed me most of the topic on strengths. It was the first time that I was told about my strengths by other people thoroughly. My top five strengths are learner, futuristic, individualism, focus and intellection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​#### Now what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utilizing these strengths are my next step. I believe that the five elements can help me to achieve my goal in the fastest way. I also believe that I can further define my passion and my role in the community with the guidance of these five words.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry><entry><title>Protege Undergraduate Research Reflection</title><link href="https://liu2z2.github.io/articles/20160901-protege-undergraduate-research-reflection" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Liu</name></author><id>tag:liu2z2.github.io,2016-09-01:/articles/20160901-protege-undergraduate-research-reflection</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During Protégé Undergraduate Research Program, I worked in Dr. Rashmi Jha’s MIND lab on a project “Electrical Simulation of Neural Signals”. The program lasted four months, during which I researched on this topic as a full-time research student. For most of my time of research, I read books and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During Protégé Undergraduate Research Program, I worked in Dr. Rashmi Jha’s MIND lab on a project “Electrical Simulation of Neural Signals”. The program lasted four months, during which I researched on this topic as a full-time research student. For most of my time of research, I read books and literature, took notes, conducted experiment in the lab, collected data, analyzed the data and crafted my own design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience had teached me a lot of academic knowledge that I am about to learn in the incoming years (MOSFETs, amplifiers, microcontrollers, SPICE simulations, etc.), as well as some hands-on skills such as using different measuring instruments and soldering. In addition, this was my first time being an actual researcher in a lab so I have built a concept what it feels like to be in academia. My lab colleague were kind and patient to explain things I did not know. Despite their eagerness to accomplish their goal, one must finish this job on his/her own. This also involves the awareness of intellectual properties. I also learned effective ways to deliver information to different kinds of audience, for example, writing documentation and make presentation in a symposium. On the other hand, by studying on the concept of neuromorphic computing and trying to understand what other lab members have been doing, I have a general idea of how current technology has advanced and how I can participate into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to present my poster as a sample work of this experience. This summarizes in detail what I learned, what I wanted to do and what I accomplished. It is self-explanatory, informative and targeted to general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly I hope this experience will help me clarify my academic interests and pave my way in the future. I might ask Dr. Jha to include me in her lab again in the incoming semesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/discuss-protege.webp"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Discussion"></category><category term="UHP"></category></entry></feed>